Larry Lowenthal Collection 1999.0113
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Larry Lowenthal Collection
undated, 1912, 1920s, 1980s-2008
1999.0113
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
3.5 Linear feet Four boxes and one large folder
Larry Lowenthal, born in 1940, is a resident of Brimfield, Massachusetts, and author of Titanic Railroad: the Southern New England, the Story of New England's Last Great Railroad War (Brimfield, MA: Marker Press, 1998). The collection consists of research files, chapter drafts, copies of original documents, and newspaper clippings of material gathered by Mr. Lowenthal when he wrote his book. The collection also consists of information about the history of New London, Connecticut, including copies of National Register of Historic Places nomination forms.
3.5 linear feet.
Lowenthal, Larry, 1940-
Biography
Larry Lowenthal, born in 1940, is a resident of Brimfield, Massachusetts, and author of Titanic Railroad: the Southern New England, the Story of New England's Last Great Railroad War (Brimfield, MA: Marker Press, 1998). He received his bachelor's degree in history from Rutgers University (1967) and a master's degree in history from Yale University (1969). He worked at the Springfield [Massachusetts] Armory National Historic Site from 1979 to 1992, and then with the Boston Support Office of the National Park Service from 1992 to 1999. He retired from the National Park Service on December 31, 1999, and is now a historical consultant and writer.
Mr. Lowenthal is also the author of Iron Mine Railroads of Northern New Jersey (Dover, N.J.: Tri-State Railway Historical Society, 1981), The Lackawanna Railroad in Northwest New Jersey (Morristown, N.J.: Tri-State Railway Historical Society, 1987), From the Coalfields to the Hudson: a History of the Delaware & Hudson Canal (Fleischmanns, N.Y.: Purple Mountain Press, 1997), and Marinus Willett, Defender of the Northern Frontier (Fleischmanns, NY: Purple Mountain Press, 2000).
Scope and Content
The collection consists of research files, chapter drafts, copies of original documents, photographic prints and negatives, and newspaper clippings of material gathered by Mr. Lowenthal when he wrote his book Titanic Railroad. The collection is organized by type of material (chapter drafts, copies of correspondence, typed masters) under the categories devised by Larry Lowenthal. All the materials were gathered in the 1980s and 1990s, though the some of the copies themselves are of publications or manuscripts created in the late 1800s or early 1900s.
The collection also consists of information about the history of New London, Connecticut, including copies of National Register of Historic Places nomination forms.
Bibliography
Iron Mine Railroads of Northern New Jersey, Dover, N.J.: Tri-State Railway Historical Society, 1981.
The Lackawanna Railroad in Northwest New Jersey, Morristown, N.J.: Tri-State Railway Historical Society, 1987.
From the Coalfields to the Hudson: a History of the Delaware & Hudson Canal, Fleischmanns, N.Y.: Purple Mountain Press, 1997.
Titanic Railroad: the Southern New England, the Story of New England's Last Great Railroad War, Brimfield, MA: Marker Press, 1998.
Marinus Willett, Defender of the Northern Frontier, Fleischmanns, NY: Purple Mountain Press, 2000.
Acquisition Information
The collection was previously in the possession of Larry Lowenthal, and was donated directly by him to Archives & Special Collections in December 1999 with small additions made in August and October 2000, and in June 2012.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of railroad materials. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
Hays, Charles Melville, 1856-1912.; Mellen, Charles S., 1851-1927, (Charles Sanger).; Morgan, J. Pierpont (John Pierpont), 1837-1913.; Author.; Correspondence.; Galley proofs.; Grand Trunk Railway; Manuscripts.; Photocopies.; Photographic negatives.; Photographic prints.; Publications.; Southern New England Railroad Co.; Southern New England Railway Co.
- Series I: Titanic Railroad research materials, 1980s-2000
  - Photocopied maps (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Titanic Railroad original illustrations (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Titanic Railroad draft with corrections (chapters 1-3) [Note: Chapters 1-3 were later combined, and the published book has eleven chapters] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Titanic Railroad draft with corrections (chapters 4-6) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Titanic Railroad draft with corrections (chapters 7-8) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Titanic Railroad draft with corrections (chapters 9-10) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Titanic Railroad draft with corrections (chapters 11-13) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Titanic Railroad revised draft (foreword and chapter 1) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Titanic Railroad revised draft (chapters 2-4) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Titanic Railroad revised draft (chapters 5-6) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Titanic Railroad revised draft (chapters 7-8) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Titanic Railroad revised draft (chapters 9-10) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Titanic Railroad revised draft (chapters 11-13) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Titanic Railroad photo and caption information (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Southern New England Railroad newspaper clippings and typescript copies of original documents (1909-September 13, 1911) (Folder 1 of 6) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Southern New England Railroad newspaper clippings and typescript copies of original documents (September 15, 1911-October 20, 1912) (Folder 2 of 6) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Southern New England Railroad newspaper clippings and typescript copies of original documents (January 3, 1913-August 11, 1914) (Folder 3 of 6) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Southern New England Railroad newspaper clippings and typescript copies of original documents (January 3, 1913-August 11, 1914) (Folder 4 of 6) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Southern New England Railroad newspaper clippings and typescript copies of original documents (August 17, 1914-November 18, 1921) (Folder 5 of 6) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Southern New England Railroad newspaper clippings and typescript copies of original documents (November 19, 1921-March 28, 1937) (Folder 6 of 6) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Southern New England Railroad newspaper clippings: background (photocopies) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Providence Board of Trade Journal/Providence Magazine (photocopies) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Poor's Manual of Railroads 1918 ( Central Vermont Railway Co., leased lines) (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Synopsis of original documents not photocopied by Mr. Lowenthal (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Additional notes from annual reports of Railroad Commissioners and Public Service Commission (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Notes and transcriptions of writings by Charles S. Mellen (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Notes of Central Vermont Railway directors meeting minutes (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Typed masters (typescript copies of original documents, 1863-February 17, 1912) (Folder 1 of 6) (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Typed masters (typescript copies of original documents, February 18-October 21, 1912) (Folder 2 of 6) (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Typed masters (typescript copies of original documents, November 11-December 25, 1912) (Folder 3 of 6) (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Typed masters (typescript copies of original documents, January 3, 1913-July 23, 1914) (Folder 4 of 6) (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Typed masters (typescript copies of original documents, July 30, 1914-March 15, 1923) (Folder 5 of 6) (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Typed masters (typescript copies of original documents, April 7, 1925-January 6, 1932) (Folder 6 of 6) (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Photocopies of photographs of highway bridges over the Southern New England Railroad right of way in the town of Dudley, Massachusetts (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Reports advocating for the construction of the Southern New England Railroad, undated, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Southern New England Railroad articles (Folder 1 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Southern New England Railroad articles (Folder 2 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Titanic Railroad follow-up (articles, pictures, and correspondence) (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Documents about Titanic Railroad generated prior to publication (articles, pictures, and correspondence) (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Mr. Lowenthal's correspondence containing Southern New England Railroad information (Folder 1 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Mr. Lowenthal's correspondence containing Southern New England Railroad information (Folder 2 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Studies to determine the future course of action of the Southern New England Railroad by the Canadian National Railways (Folder 1 of 2), ca. 1920s (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Studies to determine the future course of action of the Southern New England Railroad by the Canadian National Railways (Folder 2 of 2), ca. 1920s (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Copies of financial reports of the Central Vermont Railway (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Mr. Lowenthal's handwritten notes on photocopies from research (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Copies of reports about electrification of railroad lines between New London, Connecticut, and Brattleboro, Vermont (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Copies of the by-laws of the Southern New England Railway (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Copies of meeting minutes of the board of directors of the Southern New England Railroad (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Photocopies of Interstate Commerce Commission finance docket about Central Vermont Railroad, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Southern New England Railroad: articles on related railroads (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Photocopies of and notes about Southern New England Railroad real estate (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Photocopies of correspondence and reports about building of the Southern New England Railroad (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - New Haven Railroad records from the Karl Stieg collection including Southbridge and Sturbridge, Massachusetts, land transactions (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Notes on the case "U.S.A. versus Charles S. Mellen, Edson J. Chamberlain, and Alfred F. Smithers" (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Earl H. Fitzhugh lawsuits, Merrimack County, New Hampshire, Superior Court, 1913, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Information on the Central Vermont Railroad's "Green Mountain Route" and the Boston and Maine Railroad (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Copies of Massachusetts district court suits relevant to the Southern New England Railroad (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Copies of documents about Charles Mellen (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Hays statue in Prince Rupert, British Columbia (photos, articles, and letters) (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Copies of state records, Massachusetts, involving the Southern New England Railroad (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Doug Moore photos of Hays cemetery plot and Montreal GT Headquarters (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Biographical material about Charles M. Hays (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Biographical information about individuals mentioned in the Titanic Railroad (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Photocopies of Central Vermont Railway timetables, parlor and sleeping car schedules (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - A Brief History of Westville, Shuttleville and the Dennison District Area, by John Boniface (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Evidence taken before the relative to the financial transactions of the Company, together with the report of the Commission thereon (Folder 1 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Evidence taken before the relative to the financial transactions of the Company, together with the report of the Commission thereon (Folder 2 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Publicity about book and programs given by Mr. Lowenthal to promote the Titanic Railroad (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Callboy, Vol. 54, No. 6. A publication of the Massachusetts Bay Railroad Enthusiasts, Inc. (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Tour buttons, name tags, photograph, and slides from Massachusetts Bay Railroad Enthusiasts tour of Southern New England Railroad, April 15, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - 5.25" diskettes of files of chapters (copied to 3.5" disks, updated to Microsoft Word) (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Photocopies of newspapers articles with information about walking tours given by Mr. Lowenthal of Southern New England Railroad roadbeds, October 2000 (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - Maps of the route of the Southern New England Railroad and of some cities and towns along the route, including Pawtucket, East Providence and Central Falls, Rhode Island (Item 4)
  - Photographic prints and negatives used for the book or are associated with the Southern New England Railroad, correspondence to Larry Lowenthal regarding the book (2008); copies of newspaper clippings about the SNER; materials (including photographs and pamphlets) associated with the history of New London, Connecticut, including copies of National Register of Historic Places Inventory - Nomination Forms, 1990s-2008 (Box 5)